<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epitaph of the vertuous life and death of the right worshipfull ladie, Dame Helen Branch of London widow, late the wife of Sir Iohn Branch Knight, sometime the right honourable Lord Maior of London, and daughter to M. William Nicolson sometime of London draper : vvhich said ladie, deceased on VVednesday the 10. of April last past, and lieth interred in the parish church of S. Mary Abchurch in London, the 29. of the same moneth, 1594.</title>
            <author>S. P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19078.4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1328</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22122754</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22122754</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25109</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25109)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1732:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epitaph of the vertuous life and death of the right worshipfull ladie, Dame Helen Branch of London widow, late the wife of Sir Iohn Branch Knight, sometime the right honourable Lord Maior of London, and daughter to M. William Nicolson sometime of London draper : vvhich said ladie, deceased on VVednesday the 10. of April last past, and lieth interred in the parish church of S. Mary Abchurch in London, the 29. of the same moneth, 1594.</title>
                  <author>S. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: S.P.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Branch, Hellen, --  Lady, d. 1594 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25109:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <p>AN Epitaph of the vertuous life and death of the right worſhipfull Ladie, Dame <hi>Helen Branch</hi> of London widow, late the wife of ſir <hi>Iohn Branch</hi> Knight, ſometime the Right honourable Lord Maior of London, and daughter to M. <hi>William Nicolſon</hi> ſometime of London Draper:</p>
            <p>VVhich ſaid Ladie, deceaſed on VVedneſday the 10. of April laſt paſt: and lieth interred in the pariſh Church of S. Mary Abchurch in London, the 29. of the ſame moneth. 1594.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>VERITAS VIRESSIT VVLNERE</p>
               <p>T C</p>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Thomas Creede. 1594.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:25109:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:25109:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <head>An Epitaph of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous life and death of the Right worſhipfull Ladie, Dame <hi>Helen Branch</hi> of London widow, late the wife of Sir <hi>Iohn Branch</hi> Knight, ſometime the right honorable Lord Maior of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and daughter of M. <hi>William Nicolſon</hi> ſometime of London Draper: Which ſaid Lady deceaſed on Wedneſday the 10. of <hi>Aprill laſt past: And lieth interred in the pariſh Church of S. Mary Abchurch in London, the</hi> 29. <hi>of the ſame moneth.</hi> 1594.</head>
            <l>SInce that all liuing things we ſee, on earth that draweth breath,</l>
            <l>Do at the laſt returne to duſt, and yeeld themſelues to death:</l>
            <l>So death vnto the godly ones, is happie end of wo,</l>
            <l>For then doth come the end of cares, that toſſe vs too and fro.</l>
            <l>This world is full of ſnares and trappes, temptations vnto ſinne,</l>
            <l>As well in generations paſt, as this that we liue in.</l>
            <l>Compare our ſelues vnto a tree, which ſpringeth vp with ſap,</l>
            <l>And brings forth branches goodly ones, which taſte of Adams hap.</l>
            <l>And as this tree doth grow to ſtrength, the owner of the wood,</l>
            <l>May lop away the branches faire, as them which are not good.</l>
            <l>So hath he lopt away from vs a Ladie <hi>Branch</hi> of price,</l>
            <l>That liued here right worſhipfull, diſdaining euery vice:</l>
            <l>Whoſe lacke her friends do much bewaile, but ſpecially the poore,</l>
            <l>Whom ſhe continually did feede, abroad, and at her doore.</l>
            <l>Right beautifull, and fane was ſhe, in feature and in face,</l>
            <l>A modeſt and a vertuous Dame, indued with great grace:</l>
            <l>Daughter to maiſter <hi>Nicolſon,</hi> a Draper wiſe and ſage,</l>
            <l>A man well giuen to honour God, as well in youth as age.</l>
            <l>She from her infancie in youth, did leade a vertuous life,</l>
            <l>To Maiſter <hi>Mynors</hi> ſage and graue, ſhe firſt became a wife.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:25109:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
She iſſue had by him, one ſonne, and daughters alſo three,</l>
            <l>Which all departed very yoong, as Deſtinies decree.</l>
            <l>When Maiſter <hi>Mynors</hi> yeelded life to God that gaue the ſame,</l>
            <l>To ſir <hi>Iohn Branch,</hi> then late Lord Maior, ſhe was the ſpouſed Dame.</l>
            <l>Right godly and right vertuouſly, they liued long in ioy,</l>
            <l>With deeds of hoſpitalitie, whereas they ſaw annoy.</l>
            <l>Vnto the Drapers Hall alſo, ſhe in her life time free,</l>
            <l>Gaue fiftie pounds to yoong mens vſe, of that good companie:</l>
            <l>From foure yeares vnto foure yeares, ſtill remaining without charge,</l>
            <l>Which was a deed of charitie, and bountie paſſing large.</l>
            <l>In Abchurch pariſh where ſhe dwelt, the poore ſhe alwaies fed,</l>
            <l>With mony, meat, with coales for fire, ſomtimes with drink &amp; bread.</l>
            <l>To the Lunatickes of Bethelem, ſhe gaue right needfull things,</l>
            <l>And not one priſon ſhe forgate, from faith ſuch fruite oft ſprings.</l>
            <l>To Maydes to helpe their marriages, (I meane the poorer ſort,)</l>
            <l>She left reliefe as bountifull, vnto their great comfort.</l>
            <l>To Oxford, &amp; to Cambridge both, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence good learning flows,</l>
            <l>She hath them giuen liberallie, as ſequell plainly ſhowes.</l>
            <l>To the Hoſpitals of London too, ſhe gaue a great reward,</l>
            <l>And to the poore good ſtore of gownes, ſhe tooke ſo good regard.</l>
            <l>And as ſhe liued a vertuous life, ſo godly was her end,</l>
            <l>The which in letters all of gold, deſerues well to be pend.</l>
            <l>And now mee-thinkes I ſee and view, the holie Lambe to greet her,</l>
            <l>The Angels and Archangels too, and all the Saints to meet her.</l>
            <l>Mee-thinkes I ſee old <hi>Abraham,</hi> vnbracing of his breſt:</l>
            <l>Saving bleſſed <hi>Branch</hi> come here and ſleepe, and take thy quiet reſt.</l>
            <l>The Lambe ſhall wipe away thy teares, his blood hath waſht away,</l>
            <l>All worldly cares and blemiſhes, and here is perfect day.</l>
            <l>Inioy the ſweete melodious tunes, with husbands both reioyce:</l>
            <l>Sing Hims &amp; Pſalms before the throne, with ſweet &amp; pleaſant voyce.</l>
            <l>For thou haſt cloath'd the naked ones, the hungry thou haſt fed:</l>
            <l>Thou haſt bene milde and mercifull, relieuing members dead.</l>
            <l>Thou haſt not hid my Talents, nor my bleſſings in the ground:</l>
            <l>Thou haſt not bene a wauering reed, but faithfull, ſtrong, and ſound.</l>
            <l>Be thou example to the reſt, like goodneſſe to enſue:</l>
            <l>That they may ioy where thou art bleſt, thus Ladie good Adue.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
